Guide to the Kaderli collection of letters about death, 1961-1966 MS 052
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Kaderli collection of letters about death, 1961-1966
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Kaderli, Elizabeth Land
MS 052
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder)
This is a collection of twenty-seven letters, mostly handwritten and accompanied by their original envelopes. Each letter addresses the subject posed by Mrs. Kaderli when she asked for guidance in explaining death to her small daughter. A few of the letters are photocopies which replace lost originals.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth Land Kaderli was born in 1921 in Dallas, Texas. She attended Lamar High School and was a graduate of the Rice Institute in 1943. She married Robert Kaderli, Jr. after World War II. In 1954, she moved with her husband and daughter to Midland, Texas. She began writing adventure fiction for magazines (often under the name Land Kaderli), published "Twenty seconds to live" (1959), and "A girl and five brave horses" (1961) under the name Elizabeth Land. She worked as a producer for public televsion, working on "Face to Face," a weekly program on KLRN-TV in Austin, Texas. After the death of her husband in 1971, she moved to Houston, where she produced "The Greenroom," a weekly special for KUHT-TV highlighting art venues and activities throughout the city. After retiring from television in 1985, she moved to San Diego to be near her family. She returned to Houston in 1998 and lived in Houston until her death in 2017.
In the early 1960s she wrote a series of letters to leaders in the fields of art, music, literature, science, religion, medicine and other fields examining the subject of death. Responses to her letters make up the content of this collection.
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of twenty-seven letters, mostly handwritten and accompanied by their original envelopes. Each letter addresses the subject posed by Mrs. Kaderli when she asked for guidance in explaining death to her small daughter. A few of the letters are photocopies which replace lost originals. She wrote a series of letters to leaders in the fields of art, music, literature, science, religion, medicine and other fields, and the responses to her letters make up the content of this collection. Famous figures such as Sir Julian Huxley, Aldous Huxley, C.S. Lewis, Eleanor Roosevelt and Carl Sandburg replied.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift donated by Elizabeth Land Kaderli in 1997.
Index Terms
Document Types
letters (correspondence)
- Series I: Correspondence, 1961-1966, 257685
  - Moss Hart to Elizabeth Kaderli, October 11, 1961, 257712 (Letter 1)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt to Elizabeth Kaderli, October 16, 1961 (photocopy), 257711 (Letter 2)
  - Carl Sandburg to Elizabeth Kaderli, November 15, 1961, 257710 (Letter 3)
  - Julian Huxley to Elizabeth Kaderli, November 17, 1961 (photocopy), 257709 (Letter 4)
  - R. Niebuhr to Elizabeth Kaderli, November 24, 1961, 257708 (Letter 5)
  - Harlow Shapley to Elizabeth Kaderli, November 30, 1961, 257707 (Letter 6)
  - Aldous Huxley to Elizabeth Kaderli, December 31, 1961, 257706 (Letter 7)
  - Arnold Toynbee to Elizabeth Kaderli, January 26, 1962 (photocopy), 257705 (Letter 8)
  - Thomas Merton to Elizabeth Kaderli, February 24, 1962, 257704 (Letter 9)
  - Mark van Doren to Elizabeth Kaderli, February 27, 1962, 257703 (Letter 10)
  - Paul Tillich to Elizabeth Kaderli, March 7, 1962, 257702 (Letter 11)
  - Radoslav A. Tsanoff to Elizabeth Kaderli, November 20, 1962, 257701 (Letter 12)
  - C.S. Lewis to Elizabeth Kaderli, November 20, 1962, 257700 (Letter 13)
  - Graham Greene to Elizabeth Kaderli, December 17, 1962, 257699 (Letter 14)
  - Olaus J. Murie to Elizabeth Kaderli, December 18, 1962, 257698 (Letter 15)
  - William C. Menninger to Elizabeth Kaderli, December 28, 1962, 257697 (Letter 16)
  - J. Frank Dobie to Elizabeth Kaderli, December 31, 1962, 257696 (Letter 17)
  - Leonard Bernstein to Elizabeth Kaderli, December 31, 1962, 257695 (Letter 18)
  - Robert Oppenheimer to Elizabeth Kaderli, January 4, 1963, 257694 (Letter 19)
  - Loren C. Eisley to Elizabeth Kaderli, January 8, 1963 (photocopy), 257693 (Letter 20)
  - Alan Watts to Elizabeth Kaderli, January 26, 1963, 257692 (Letter 21)
  - Katherine Ann Porter to Elizabeth Kaderli, March 2, 1963, 257691 (Letter 22)
  - Bertrand Russell to Elizabeth Kaderli, March 20, 1964, 257690 (Letter 23)
  - Nelson Glueck to Elizabeth Kaderli, May 4, 1964, 257689 (Letter 24)
  - Theodor Reik to Elizabeth Kaderli, January 25, 1966, 257688 (Letter 25)
  - John Woolwich to Elizabeth Kaderli, August 4, 1966, 257687 (Letter 26)
  - John Woolwich to Elizabeth Kaderli, September 13, 1966, 257686 (Letter 27)